all
right welcome back everyone
it's February 12th and second discussion
of chapter 6 for cohor 5
so any thoughts or feelings on where to
begin with chapter
like any thought or quote or
[Music]
question I have
one yes
please
um I'm not so sure it's in this chapter
but can you go into more detail in terms
of uh the difference between the high
road and the low
road yes would anyone like to give a
thought on high road and low road in the
chapter
six so really getting to the recipe and
the cooking what are the high road and
the low
road
well one thought is chapter 6 is a
recipe for actually walking on the low
road because this is
where the generative model is
constructed and
specified so it kind of starts from
having
nothing I don't know how deep we um uh
have or or need to go into the food
maybe it's somewhere here but I mean
what are the ingredients what's the
kitchen what needs to be done in what
order that's the low road of building
any model there could be a chapter six
for a recipe for Designing SPM analysis
or designing linear regression analysis
as thousands of other guide books for
modeling are out there so in that sense
that all modeling
and
uh construction like this is low road
because it's actually
putting uh model down that's what's
similar about chapter 6 and another
recipe for basian
modeling and then the difference with
active inference is the connection
through the high road to the free energy
principle so that's in so relative to if
I were to to translate that um and you
know and I'm the model that I'm I'm
building is more of a a self-modeling
not trying to build a
software llm model um so in terms of
yeah the low the low road is is
Imagining the pathway and the high road
would be taking the pathway would that
be a way to contrast
them you know simp IC
form what would someone else say Yes um
Ali and then anyone else who raises
their
hand okay so uh the high road uh can we
described kind of topown approach to
active inference which starts by asking
some uh very fundamental questions about
uh about what's required for any Cod UN
code thing to exist and what are its
necessary
properties so uh by beginning from uh a
kind of as friston himself would call it
a near existential
nihilism uh it gradually begins to build
uh some framework which can account for
any sentient behavior that agent must
possess in order
uh in order for it to possess its
integrity and to persist through time so
that's basically uh the premise of high
road but uh on the other hand for low
road it begins by asking it it begins by
the premise of uh the existence of the
mind so here uh the the existence of the
agent or rather the predictive agent is
presupposed and then it begins to
formulate or describe uh What uh kind of
mechanisms uh can realistically
describe uh its uh predictive behavior
and it's uh I don't know brain activity
uh or
rather the way that the brain act the
brain
constructs uh the inner model or uh in
know words its generative models uh so
that's basically beginning from the
premise of the existence of mind and uh
to describe uh what kind of um
mechanisms uh that particular mind
should possess in order for it to uh to
do both inference and action in a
changing environment but ultimately they
uh they achieve similar goal but uh as
uh the I mean the name of these
approaches would suggest uh only the
approach to achieve that same goal uh is
different but then again uh they
basically try to uh I mean describe the
same kind of
behavior so
you the near existential nihilism would
uh would that um would that correlate
with let's just assume they have
agency okay so uh all right so yes
agency is a kind of I mean Central
presupposition for any kind of um any
kind of thing that can
meaningfully uh navigate through its
environment and to have any kind of goal
directed Behavior so in other words
agency is a kind of synonym for a gold
directed Behavior it can be um
obviously I mean argued whether agency
really equates uh gold directed Behavior
but that's basically as far as I
understand uh that's the meaning of
agency in active inference literature or
or at least in uh the majority of active
inference
literature thank you um Kristoff then
Andrew
yeah I just want to say that for me the
um kind of a enlightening perspective on
the on the low road um is to Simply
derive the
um
uh an equation that features a fre free
energy essentially from from Bas rule so
you can take the Bas rule um you know uh
write it in such a way that um you
substitute another distribution for the
um for the posterior distribution which
is not not generally known
um with an approximate posterior and say
like okay since I cannot know the true
posterior I'm going to approximate the
true posterior of an approximate
posterior using some kind of variational
methods and essentially using just um
the prod sum probabilities and
rearranging those equations a little bit
uh you effectively get to the point
where um you have a quantity that is
mathematically isomorphic to you know a
free energy in thermodynamics so that
that's a kind of a very mechanical
mathematical way of um teasing the the
concept of free energy out of
essentially out of nowhere right because
you start with an equation that's that's
true B base um B Rule and then you make
it slight of hand where you just simply
substitute you know Q for p and say like
this is a slightly different kind of
thing because I'm going to have a bunch
of parameters that Define what that Q
thing is and those parameters I can
somehow tweak to find how good my uh
approximate um approximate posterior is
um but because for simple um mechanical
um substitutions like that you can
derive effectively an equation that
looks like um uh free energy that's how
you just get all the way from Bas fum to
to the uh to the free energy principle
effectively so that's that's kind of
like why it's bottom up you sort of
construct it um this
way amazing thank you Andrew
oh on me
Andrew just a cute analogy I would say
that Plato would always try to start
with the high road while um Aristotle
would uh see what he's got available and
start with the low road Road and since
we're trying to implement something we
got to use the tools we have accessible
and so um chapter six is uh seeing what
we've got there and taking the low road
to uh Implement something that shows
active
inference
awesome yeah great great comments here's
figure one two it's a nice evocative
figure also though the it's not like
there's a strict sequence or like
there's any it's like um some
subway stations but it's not very strict
and it's not like all or necessary
sufficient or anything like that um but
it is situating active inference
generative models as on one hand
implementing Bas theorem giving what
Kristoff um provided this kind of
unrecognized
relationship between statistical
principles of least action which we now
call the basy mechanics and the free
energy principle and how that's like an
extension of other physics and
information and thermal
physics and yet all all of that kind of
like Theory aside chapter 6 doesn't have
an equation
chapter 6 is like actually the sequence
although they um make clear like it's
more about a checklist um than a than an
ordered sequence here um but this is the
theory um light sequence of questions
that's actually procedural like a
catechism to work towards doing a
generative model to working in active
inference and realizing the synthetic
active inference agents
whether it's about
oneself um that's human system of
Interest or whether it's about some
other
system
um that's chapter
six it's with only looks like that one
figure and not any um of these
connections that have been brought up
which are super great and well said
about the basing
mechanics
so chapter six on the low road but if
you um build it this
way then by making an active inference
model from the low road it would
be uh you could run it in pmtp so it
would be kind
of concorded with free energy
principle and we have we have many
examples we can look at we can look at
the tutorials of
pmdp we can also talk more about the
recipe of chapter 6 but that's kind of
the big idea of
six um anyone can raise their hand with
like a or
or yes I have a question yes go for it
um yes I wrote it in the chat what is
meant by the first step the
identification of boundaries and then it
says I.E Markoff blanket
but I just want to say thank you so much
for this very um elucidating explanation
for high load and Rollo I've read it
several times and this was the best or
finally it it clicked so thank
you thank you so great
question Alie want to go for it or how
does it come into play in in the process
of building a generative model yes
please yeah just wrote it in the chat as
well so markup blanket is a kind of a
statistical boundary in the state space
of the agent so in other words it can uh
manifest itself as a spatial temporal
boundary or not so in some cases for
example in U I don't know cell
boundaries or cell membranes it actually
manifests uh as uh real spatial temporal
boundary but it's not necessarily so uh
and uh it can u i mean markup blanket
can be expressed variously in different
forms for different situations uh but
basically it kind of provide uh a
necessary statistical boundary in the
state space of the agent uh in order for
uh for the agent to be uh statistically
separated from its uh so-called
environment
uh so if there wasn't any Mark of
blanket delineating the this boundary
then uh the behavior the internal
behavior of the agent uh would be
identical uh to the uh behavior of uh
the environment in which it's embedded
so uh yeah that's a necessary
presupposition for doing any kind of
active inference modeling uh around that
system
so may I ask a follow-up question yeah
sure so in the case of
swarms or plasmoids where an act an
individual agent is impacted by the
whole
group um so would the same principles
apply in characterizing the agent as the
group yeah that's very great question so
you see Mark blanket uh can be um can be
described in uh multiple scales so for
instance um even for um for so let's uh
take the brain as an example uh we can
draw a markup blanket around single
neurons or around I don't know uh
particular circuits neural circuits or
around the whole brain and even even
further than that around the whole
organism and there are some Works uh
that that have been used for
um they've used active inference for
modeling the whole um some of the social
and cultural Behavior Uh of whole uh
communities or societies so in those
cases markup blankets can be drawn
around a whole Community or Society so
basically it depends on the system of
interest uh it's not something
predefined thank you I'll give one other
example just because this swarm modeling
topic um is a great one and to give a a
specific example so when we were
simulating an ant colony and there was a
chapter 6 but this is the result of the
chapter 6 this is the specification of
the envir IR m a t maze where there
could be movement and then this is the
generative model that was specified like
the generative model of the nestmate was
the
ABCDE and the the kind of um active
inference Loop that it implemented at
each time step so in that sense it was
an agent based simulation much like net
logo or using any other agent based
simulation except that the the the
basian graph of the structure that it
was implementing was like the figure 4.3
graph so specification of the
environment specification of the um
generative model including the boundary
in space and time like having the
ability to receive um uh in a one square
perimeter so we didn't a priori set a
blanket on the colony but you could
imagine if you said okay well I'm going
to look down from the top and enclose
another blanket around the total space
that the colony encloses which might
might be meanful or might uh not be but
from the modeling perspective all that
was needed to specify was the nestmate
but then summary statistics could be
made about areas covered so there's a
lot of other um analogous examples with
multi-agent
simulations um to a first approximation
what you specify is the agents just like
any other agent based model um and then
um people are looking into as Ali
mentioned like integrating true
multiscale systems modeling like
multi-agent models of neurons
constituting circuits and so
on Andrew and then
Pros yeah just a quick note that the
Markoff blanket is best thought of as a
um
computationally uh meaningful parameter
not necessarily something that you will
be able to pin down in physical space so
for example like if you think of your
Markoff blanket it's uh associated with
the sensing and
action
um modalities you have available um
you're even though there's
physical space is going through you in
in a certain way and you are
regenerating in terms of um your
particles at a certain rate um it it's
related to how you as a computational
agent are associating with your
environment and so uh you can think of
that both from the intrinsic perspective
I just described as well as if you are
modeling something you get to pick what
is the data going into and being
processed by your statistical model and
what is the data going out and being
processed uh and transformed into
physical uh
phenomena got it thank
you thank you pros and then
Kristoff yes uh thank you uh Daniel I
have a question for you like in the ant
model which you showed I was imagining
that if we have say multiple ant and
they want to form a group by themselves
uh so will you be able to create like
kind of a markof model like a blanket
dynamically am I correct or
incorrect well few things to say on that
so first the as the blankets are
features of the maps not the territories
like it it could be possible you could
say again I'm taking a top down view of
the movement and I'm going to draw
little enclosures and I'm going to have
a thresholding parameter for when I
declare like these three to be a
separate cluster so so but at that point
that's not really like what the nestate
is doing which this whole time hasn't
changed from just as specified so
there's a lot of higher order clustering
and and partitioning methods that aren't
exactly the base level specification of
the generative model which is often
pretty small and and simple um and then
another thing to say on it is like uh as
with many agent based model like here
all they could do was um move and uh put
down one pheromone there wasn't like an
option for them to have a second pherone
or to do nursing or uh other kinds of
behavior
so um there's always kind of a limited
zone of of the like emergence or
phenomena that are displayed from a
simulation if it's really pruned down to
be
simple and then to make um
richer like more more whole iguana
simulations that's what is exciting
about active
inference uh one one followup question
on this uh so basically you are
designing it through policies which you
have or it's like more higher order
stuff this one the only policies they
could take there's no planning was just
moving in a grid like a grid world but
as with any active inference generative
model like chapter 6 describes all the
aspects of the model are specified the
input sensory any um higher order
beliefs that it entertains like the the
cognitive States than the affordances it
has how it does policy selection whether
it do planning whether it has any of
these other features like attention so
figure 4.3 which is basically what is
here um is just the minimal kernel Motif
in discrete time
and then there's all of these kind of
like features and this is a very simple
framework with the goal as most of the
published models
are and then um that's why there's so
many opportunities now to connect the
different systems of Interest with the
colonel with the motifs that are
arising um okay Francis yeah thank you
Francis oh sorry Kristoff and then
Francis then
Tanner
uh I just want to add one thing to the
um Mark of blanket concept
um slightly different perspective that
uh comes from something that um Steven
walr is working on the Observer Theory
which is he's kind of rediscovering very
similar thing to active inference but on
slightly different um um basis so he
talks about what's necessary for for
something to be on Observer and in some
sense you need to have more computation
going um going on on the inside of the
Observer and you know that's that's
going on on the outside what what is
being observed so this Mark of blanket
is the statistical definition of a mark
of blanket to me is is kind of um very
confusing right like there's this uh
statistical what does the statistical
Independence really mean well it really
means that you you know the the The
Observer or the agent is going to do
something internally that you can't
readily predict from just looking at it
without um it actually responding
somehow to the event so it has to you
know um some information is coming in it
has to process it in some way and it you
know it will react react in the
eventually in the environment and as
long as it's doing enough computation on
the inside then um
the uh it will basically become
statistically independent because you
can no longer using simple statistics or
any kind of Statistics really model uh
what is it really um what is it really
doing uh
internally and these things kind of seem
to arise naturally as uh any kind of
complex systems uh interact so so these
are kind of boundaries that on one hand
we can we can draw them somewhat
arbitrarily sometimes on the other hand
they're they're kind of naturally
arising in interactions of any kind of
um any kind of computational
systems I hope it's this is very helpful
for me but um I'm not sure if it makes
any sense in this context here yeah it's
awesome like you're you're right they
can absolutely be proposed um out of
nothing like you could just draw
arbitrary base graph and just say here's
the blanket but they also do arise
naturally seemingly um or maps with this
character describe complex systems um a
simple example of which being space um
or time like things kind of propagating
outwards in space and things not
teleporting through space like a bubble
expanding outwards not like skipping a
shell because it's like propagating
locally in space so that kind of
captures that property too as well as
the I guess as wol from is looking into
more of the computational parts of like
measuring and and
observing um Francis then Tanner and
Ali hi
so uh my first stab at understanding
marov blankets was uh from my
programming background I thought okay so
this is like a bit like having a
function or an object where you pass
parameters in which might be the
goals and then leave it to get on with
this and then maybe it'll some if
something goes wrong it'll send an
exception up to uh so that can go up the
perception the exceptions go up the
perception tra uh
hierarchy
um and
then I just been I picked up
the uh references to the
environment and I'm starting to think of
as a mark of blanket as being something
which uh because things are hidden from
the environment they're not part of the
environment therefore they can have
a is the internal State and it can be
the internal state which as an to the
intent that to the extent that it's an
agent the internal state that it is
trying to
preserve
um so it's kind of what's at stake what
it
is
um at it
being uh I guess anything which has a
barkoff
blanket um
actually what what is the answer to that
question what is it that can have a
markof
blankets uh an active
entrance okay thank
you thank you
Tanner okay so yeah I have a I do have a
question that I want to ask but first I
um I want to respond to the last
participants query um I think the the
issue that a lot of people have when
trying to understand what marov blankets
and marov boundaries are is they like
make it too agential in the sense of
like the words that they use just become
agent identified
like the way that I understand it is
that marov boundaries are agents right
so so we say but it's important to
understand that marov blankets aren't
actually extent in like material reality
they're just ideas right they're like
this is like this is the boundary um so
you know it it you can sort of
understand this if you like think about
it and you're like you know I so I see a
spider right and I'm like that's a
spider that's that's an
individual but is it like you just kind
of made that definition right you you
assigned the you drew the Line in the
Sand right you you know circled The
Spider and we're like that's that's the
entity right there that's the agent with
identified active awareness doing the
inferential you know
stuff it's kind of arbitrary so marov
blankets are like
defined in this uh you know more hor
horis way like they are they are
emergent properties that do exist like
they they do they exist in a qualitative
sense um you know most of the time I'm
existing as as a person in a body but in
a state of meditation you can sort of
start to exist with a larger or just
different marov blanket that includes
maybe other people the room Etc so
that's that's all I wanted to say about
that it's not
it's not one to one right there's
there's there's this there's a whole
Spectrum to these things um anyway my
question was about spiders so you uh
were you have these models um that you
were presenting about ants and my
curiosity is uh ants have this as I
understand largely two-dimensional kind
of experience where it's like left right
you know they're not really moving up
down it's it's very much so just like
follow the fairmon trail um and you can
correct me if I'm wrong because you know
much much more about this than I do but
my my question was like if you were
trying to extend that uh this model that
you've created to a spider which is
something that exists in in a very
three-dimensional way and even in in
some sense in like a four dimensional
way because the whole concept of
building a web is like working with a
plan that is a long-term plan to catch
and exist right it builds a home for
itself that's not something a drone ant
is doing I don't think so just curious
what you kind of think about that idea
if just take like a a classical like
field spider as an example um and and I
would I would love to to hear your
thoughts on that in comparison to your
model
so okay just very briefly um the Markov
blanket is definitely not associated
with just the agent environment
interface like this node is a blanket
between X and Y so the markup blanket
can be identified between any nodes but
one kind of interest is this agentic and
and definitely it it's like very um
Observer dependent like all observation
is how agentic different boundaries are
seen as and um to the spider I mean this
is what chapter 6 is about
please look through chapter 6 and mega
spider model and then next week let's
look at it and we'll further along and
maybe we can even you know go from there
but that's exactly what chapter 6 is
about yeah um do you have a
recommendation do you have a
recommendation of a particular species I
should look at or I can find one I I
mean from the beginning of when you're
feeling curious about the phenomena on
through the active inference model you
make just document it and then it'll be
done okay cool thank you Daniel I
appreciate it thank
you uh so uh little bit I think u a more
sophisticated uh version of Mark of
blanket I'm not sure if it's directly uh
inspired by the concept of markco
blanket or not may or may not be but uh
there's this uh important paper by
Michael 11 one of its um I believe one
of the most highly cited ones the
computational boundary of a cell from
2019 uh in which he develops uh the
concept of scale-free cognition and the
idea is that there's this computational
boundary or as um as he describes it in
this paper a kind of light cone a
cognitive light cone that can Define uh
the scale of the agent's cognition um I
mean through various scales and various
limits of the cognition so it's not
restricted uh to uh even a single scale
of interest uh it can be uh
modeled u in a in a true hierarchical
way to include uh various um scales and
various limitations of cognition even if
we want to kind of investigate the
interaction uh between uh or among um
the various scales of cognition and the
other uh related um conception uh was
developed by uh David kraar at all and
their 2020 paper the information theory
of individuality in which they again uh
describe a kind of U information
theoretical conception of uh what it
means to be a biological individual so
uh this information theory of
individuality uh enables uh the
identification of uh of the agents at uh
any level of organization I mean from uh
even molecular uh
molecular level to even the cultural
ones uh so uh these recent con Concepts
uh can be seen as kind of update on the
or we can look at them as kind of Mark
of blanket 2.0 but I believe uh
familiarity with these newer Concepts
can uh even help us to understand uh the
nature of Mark of blanket uh I mean uh
more clearly uh than just looking at the
Active inference literature because I
agree that this concept can seem a
little bit vague uh for newcomers uh or
even for experts as well uh so I highly
recommend those two papers as
well thank you Lee yeah a few comments
on that like the markof blanket concept
comes from the causal basian modeling
literature and then there's various
extensions and kind of of analogous the
the the blanket index all these other
things um to kind of uh I mean bring it
to a more low road
building does anyone want to look at the
questions or share some of their
modeling experiences or we could look at
the PDP
tutorials because the end of chapter 6
not not like it only has to be about
this chapter but the end of chapter 6 um
doesn't necessarily leave
one
um further along or scratching their
head about these uh like multiscale
systems uh except through the
construction and often like going
through and talking through and building
through a system gets really far and
then even the theory questions from
there are more
informed
so it's not like the theory has to be
resolved
like
before one builds anything okay got it
that's useful like the PDP tutorials are
are we or or does anyone want to look at
or what would be helpful in our last
bit I I think like yeah we should
if everybody agrees
pmdp yeah um so
like let's do it there are some uh I
think a model stream 7.1 and two with
Connor Hines and Daphne dcus um like but
those are long videos and um also
contain a lot more of like
the the background on
pmdp um so I just put it into the
chapter
six okay so um I
mean the big picture on what's going to
happen here and how this is different
than chapter six this is not um this
notebook itself is not um a supplemental
dish to chapter six however with some
very slight tweaks it could be so just
to kind of set set the scene like
chapter six is a sequence of questions
it's a catechism basically for going
from your curiosity
to the constructed model so what system
are we modeling are we modeling one
spider three spiders three spiders in a
web three spiders in two webs five
spiders on N webs two trees you know
just that is not a trivial question what
are you modeling and so figuring this
out is what they have as the first
question then
what's the appropriate form of the
generative
model one big distinction being like
figure 4.3 discrete time or continuous
time and all the strengths and
weaknesses of these different um
techniques um also pmdp is like only for
discreete time models right now but
there's other approaches for continuous
time modeling um then what's the
structure of the generative model is it
an estimate that can move two two
squares forward or one Square the side
or this way diagonally or how many
phermones and how many uh does it have a
tension and if it doesn't have those
features it's not going to have them if
it doesn't have three-step time Horizon
planning your generative model will not
have that feature like if it doesn't
have planning in the code it will not do
planning now that doesn't mean it won't
give behavior that looks very
interesting in other ways but actually
that's a feature because you can say
through the fully synthetic nature of
the model it doesn't do planning and yet
this is happening um or it doesn't have
a preference for this and yet this is
happening and then what they leave for
last is like how to set up the
generative process however um as Ali and
uh asked Maxwell ramstead on in the
guest
stream they have kind of moved away that
group and of modelers not saying this is
the the only the best way they've moved
away from distinguishing so much between
generative model and process because in
the end they're co- defined and in like
complex systems it's not so simple it's
like which one's the agent which one's
the environment it's like well there's
two agents communicating so you know why
not just call it all the generative
model um okay so chapter six gets us to
writing the pseudo code basically that
we're going to look at the python code
for
um what they were going for here their
goal was um you know if if we were to
apply the chapter 6 question is to model
an agent that moves in this um 3x3 maze
grid world and has a preference for a
certain
location and you can copy the the um
code this package that they have written
is called
PDP um and it also is bringing in just a
few math
packages this box this is tutorial one
this box has some kind of um just purely
visualization based functions like
plotting likelihood this is not like an
active inference
box um also as some of my friends have
remarked from computer science is like
there's some pros and cons to notebooks
on one hand they can be be copied really
easily and run in the cloud like on a
Chromebook but at the same time it can
like lead to a lot of like okay I
thought we were going to do active
inference but then no it's like this
other thing is happening first so it's
not always clear what's what's happening
even what because it's so
linearized
um
okay here they're just showing what this
function does and plotting a categorical
distribution
so it's it's kind of built it's like a
little step by step this is not building
the agent yet then from just doing this
is like a three-sided coin
flip now the other kind of key piece of
the Bas formula is going to come into
play which is conditional
probabilities and they show doing some
conditional probabilities just to show
in PDP like what we're doing is
probabilities and conditional
probabilities like the The Joint
distribution of the nesme is just the
joint distribution of a b c and d that
totally describes the nestmate there's
no other information about the nestmate
and then conditional probabilities
become really important because like
we're often interested in conditional
distributions like the distribution of
action conditioned upon dis
observation other things like that okay
so that that was all like kind of
preliminary
like
PDP utilities and just demonstrating the
syntax kind of now they're going to go
into grid
World
okay the grid is specified it's a 3X3
grid that's specified as this um set of
ordered
pairs and then it's visualized with
their graphing
function
so that's the generative process that's
basically the environment is being
specified now just like for other
discreete time active inference agents
what there is to specify is a b c and
d so just to the figure uh or
chapter 7 where it go which is the next
chapter which goes into more detail on
the discrete time model so a b c and d a
b c going into um G here's C because
policy distribution is conditioned upon
preference and habit so it's just kind
of getting wrapped into this G
visualization a b c
d first they generate a a is the
conditional distribution that is
basically mapping between observations
and hidden States
so um in this world each of these
locations is going to um just it's
basically labeled like with its location
so it has like a perfect um
GPS um so the dimensionality of a is set
the dimensionality of a is basically
like observations mapping to Hidden
States it's a matrix that describes that
mapping and so they're the same in this
case then it's made out with zeros just
to initiate it and then it's filled on
the diagonal with ones which corresponds
to perfect mapping of States if the a
matrix were flat there'd be no
information about the world coming in
ETC here it's the identity Matrix so
it's just a noisess
mapping that's what it looks like so
here white square is one likelihood
black square is zero likelihood and then
it's mapping from the nine observations
to the nine hidden States and it looks
exactly this like if you see a three it
always maps to being in state
three here and then um they make a noisy
a with some different noise patterns so
here observation zero is ambiguous
whether it maps to 01 or three so
following in the grand SPM tradition
even very large generative models can be
specified like with these grayscale heat
Maps it's actually really
cool two ambiguous locations now six is
ambiguous as well okay so that's a so we
have a few different a matrices as with
other modeling it's never just about one
one perfect model that describes like
the spider it's about like having
multiscale portfolios of a matrices and
composing them and and displaying like
like this one has this behavior and
think it's cuz this but actually here's
this other model that shows that it's
not so it's it's not just about making
one it's about like doing a lot of
models and sweeping across them now they
go on to b b is the hidden State
transition um each slice of B is going
to describe the mapping from one world
State at past time point to the next
time point and then different slices of
B get selected based upon the um policy
selection so B is the critical variable
in active inference this is where the
action dependent World model is
specified and like this is really the
variable that explodes a lot with model
complexity because the D variable is
just a prior on world States so it's
just a vector that kicks the chain off
one time with like an initial
Distribution on room temperature and a
is a sens sensory mapping from
thermometer reading to the hidden State
and then C is just a preference over
thermometer readings so all of the work
in the model with the action dependent
causality all of it is in B it's
basically the only place they can go
just in practice so bees created these
are the affordances they're called
actions in this
script um there are five of them up down
left right
stay
um a few pieces are uh just
visualized and just checking through
that uh they can advance the next state
and then um like take the action and
move from
here and then move right one square to
here
then move down to here so that's
B then
C they zero it out C has the same length
as observations because it's a
distribution over observations and here
it's given a value of one for eight and
zeros for the
rest and then D has a length of the
number of world
States and it's a distribution of our
world States and so here it starts 100%
of the time state
zero and that's just how it is so that's
that's the ABCD
specification that's all of the so at
every single time Point all of the all
that the agent simulation is one agent
or multi-agent it's just a b c and d for
each agent in this most simple
example then they make some um functions
in first state that's like the making
part and this just describes the pseudo
code for going from the
observations combining that with a prior
and returning um Q of hidden state that
we discussed Q of X earlier
today they do a Time step of just the
sensemaking
inference including with the ambiguous
priors so that's the sensemaking part
then action selection this is the action
part um some more functions are
introduced pretty cool to see the uh
entropy and the K Divergence just toine
so
shortly they just kind of replot things
and just kind of refresh where it's all
at change the preference to five
add a few um print
statements
compare the expected free energy for
moving left versus moving right
classical approach you have your
affordances that are being considered
here just those two just for clarity in
the tutorial and then EF G is calculated
for those
two and then a softmax is applied such
that the units of G are normalized to
probability
distribution and then here is the
whole um grid
world and then they all wrap it together
and then they just output how it happens
and then there's a few more details and
then they add planning at the end but
everything above this point is no
planning and then from this point you
you start to see the
planning I hope that's useful um and
that people make also other tutorials or
maybe contribute edits to
PDP because there's a lot of experience
with
modeling that people have that that
could really
help and it's it's um really fun with
the theory but also it's a very specific
modeling
possibility and we have the
um there's there's so for for those with
computer experience many of these will
be
accessible um for people with less
coding
experience like it will be really
helpful to figure out and like
colearn what
approaches um are exciting for you
because this is the low
route a low
route it's a simple model but it it kind
of is it helps calibrate and
Benchmark like if this is um a big pill
then you know simulating 500 social
agents with memory is probably a really
challenging project for you if this is
very simple and
understandable then you can probably
start to Benchmark what kinds of models
you'll be able to understand or or at
least um iterate on starting
tomorrow okay any questions in the
last five minutes or thoughts on like
this modeling topic as that's kind of
chapter
six
yes prau and anyone else uh yes I was
actually I think uh first thing I what
I'll have to do is I'll have to just uh
do this tutorial once like it's very
nice you have given a brief summary of
it so it'll be very helpful if you do it
today or tomorrow um and I was I was
thinking like if if the if the Matrix is
what you mentioned over here if that is
like we have various con Concepts like
various class data structur we know very
well so similarly if you know this
matrices quite well then I think things
will just flow that's what I understand
out of
it right thank you yes totally and also
um the the model presented here is a
pretty um common
PDP that's what gives the continuity
with the computer science and the base
graph and everything like that that it
is just a PDP
basically and and yet it's um about that
Motif and then about understanding it in
the single agent case and then just kind
of building from there so like a lot of
the the work and the challenge in
application look forward to everyone
also sharing their experiences on this
is like even building one agent and then
there's like the just like Crea the
environment with n but also people are
making amazing toolkits to help
facilitate multi otive simulations so
just like everyone keep you know
learning and exploring and the tools
really are getting better fast
Susan um so I'm um my head's around how
to integrate this with the Constructor
law and I'm wondering where um degrees
of
freedom show up
in this particular
chapter you pointing
to
yes in the narrow not necessarily in the
software but I in the real world oh I
mean the chapter describes several of
the mega degrees total degrees of
freedom like okay what is the system
we're
modeling and who are we doing it for and
why I mean these are the ultimate
degrees of modular Freedom h
and then these distributions have their
own statistical degrees of
freedom okay so it really is the
construct of freedom is is kind of
underlying it's kind of you know under
the soil you might say of the uh of the
blanket so the perception of someone's
Freedom may actually correlate with
where they see their boundaries where
they see their Market boundaries I
almost want to say say that um if I were
to transfer translate the the market the
markof blankets you know to a you know a
okay metaphor it's not perfect but an
okay metaphor it would almost be the
protective boundaries that we um that we
perceive in the world which has a lot to
do with you know our perception of
Freedom would that
be however you feel
all right yeah that trying to stay with
the rigor um say I don't want to use
something that doesn't it's completely
off like I love that you added it I
don't know if they talk about Freedom at
all in the book so in in the letter of
the book no but I really like what you
added so okay thank you thank you
everyone peace see you next week also
feel free to do the tutorials add
questions add notes and like your
experiences if you were familiar with
the code or not and all of this could be
really fun so see you next time bye
thank you everyone thank you that was
great awesome bye